Oliver Diamond

diamond.oliver@gmail.com | 07846 394 258

I am a full-stack developer with many years programming experience across many languages and technologies.

Recently I have been developing FX services for HSBC's commercial corporate payments application (JS, Clojure, Java).

I'm passionate about: ES6, Lisps & functional programming; Linux architecture; and methodologies that emphasise devops, fast delivery, clean code, & developer anarchy.

Background

I have been programming since I was 13 – building web MMORPGs with friends (HTML & PHP) with 1000s of players. At university ($2:1 \ Physics$) I spent 2 years programming a bio-ecosystem simulation (C++).

I have worked in many different fields: politics, film production, TV & theatre development, and finance. However, I have pushed technological solutions across all of these industries - usually developing the applications myself): databasing apps (PHP, MySQL & PostgresSQL), training apps (Java & VBA in MS Access), financial risk and price analysis apps (C++), bespoke websites (PHP, JS, & Python), & web applications (Ruby on Rails). I have also given digital advice across many different organisations and projects.

I have trained at Makers Academy (the UK's top developer training camp), **gaining professional full-stack skills**, focussing on OO and functional programming and modern software development methodologies.

At HSBC I learned about pushing new approaches to software within an old large organisation. I became **a believer in devops, developer support, microservices, and developer freedom**. My team worked with those philosophies despite the heavily regulated and bureaucratic environment – and also aimed to demonstrate their benefits while continuously delivering value to clients and customers. My code is in now production at HSBC – still delivering value.

Skills

Programming:

- JavaScript (ES6, Node, Express, Dojo, JQuery, RxJS, Selenium) 6+ yrs
- Clojure (Compojure) 1+ yrs
- Java (Android, Spring) 2+ yrs
- Ruby (Rails) 1yr
- C++ 3+ yrs
- Python
- HTML, HTML5, CSS, LESS
- DB (MySQL PostgreSQL, Mongo)

Delivery/Ops:

- Continuous Delivery (Jenkins, TeamCity, Heroku)
- Version control: Git, RTC
- Linux (Redhat, Debian, Ubuntu)
- Bash
- Networking (DNS, TCP/IP, HTTPS)
- Eclipse, IntelliJ, Android Studio (though I prefer a text editor where possible)

Methodologies:

- Devops (Fast release cycles)
- Agile (lots of retrospecting)
- Test Driven Development
- Behaviour Driven Development
- Pairing
- Microservices Architectures
- MVC Architectures

Other Expertise

Government: I have 8 years experience across Government, public policy, and the digital & cultural industries. I continue to support a political network for those sector.

Finance: Aside from my work in HSBC's FX department, I have also worked in a credit trading hedge fund, a Chinese event-driven brokerage, and a corporate finance boutique (analysing media and tech opportunities).

Communications: I have worked on public policy campaigns, political communications, and film & theatre marketing.

Work History

HSBC GFX (Dec 2017 - Sept 2017) | DIGITAL TRANSFORMATION SOFTWARE DEVELOPER

Delivering a suite of microservices in Clojure and ES6 and interfacing them Java 6 monolith using an old JS framework.

Our team of 6 worked from within the modernising agile-embracing GFX department of the investment bank, but working to bring their products into HSBCnet, one of the world's most used commercial payment applications.

I worked in a mordern coding environment on devops, daily release cycles, developer anarchy, microservices, test-driven development and client behaviour driven development, with an ability to write code and have it in production in the same day. However simultaneously working on the HSBCnet application being developed on a quarterly release cycle, with manual testing and old SDLCs.

Makers Consultants (Dec 2015 - Present) | SOFTWARE ENGINEERING CONSULTANT

I was involved from the beginning in Makers Academy's Consultancy arm. I have remit to work on Makers' education-based platform when not with a corporate partners (HSBC, Tek Systems, & Allegis Group).

SUMS Film & Media (Aug 2015 - Dec 2015) | DIGITAL & TECHNOLOGY CONSULTANT

An independent film producer. I advised the chief executive on their project's digital strategies. I created and adivsed on various applications, including marketing websites (PHP & HTML5). (see IMDB).

Bob & Co (Nov 2014 - May 2016) | HEAD OF DIGITAL AND COMMUNICATIONS

A small media (film, TV, theatre) developer, and financier. I ran the technological, research & communication efforts. I also built (and maintained) the company website, and other applications (Java & JS) for their partners & subsidiaries.

I later became Acting Director of Operations during a staff maternity leave, tasked with extensive audit and efficiency efforts in the IT, telecoms, and other office admin budgets.

Office of the Digital & Cultural Minister (Nov 2008 - Nov 2014) | SENIOR PARLIAMENTARY ADVISOR I managed the Parliamentary office of Rt. Hon. Ed Vaizey MP from the date of his Ministerial appointment. I oversaw the running of the office, interviewing, training and managing all junior staff. I worked on campaigns such as improving Wifi provision in public libraries and bringing coding into the national curriculum.

Aside from working on digital & media policy, I was given a wide remit and free-reign within the office, so I often used programmed office solutions, developing wordpress applications (*PHP*) for websites and databasing, and MS access applications for automating emails and training.

North Square Blue Oak (Jan 2014 - Mar 2014) | SABBATICAL ANALYST

A brokerage and corporate finance boutique, assessing new corporate finance opportunities in the digital sectors. The company drew heavily on my technological expertise in assessing potential investments.

CQS Asset Management (Feb 2013 - Mar 2013) | *MARGINS DEPT ANALYST & DEVELOPMENT INTERN* A \$13bn credit hedge fund: in liability management analysis with collateral specialists (creating an app to assess marginal risks); and also with the strategic IT team, developing an (credit price monitor) application (*C#*).

Office of the MP for Wantage & Didcot (Aug 2007 - Mar 2008) | JUNIOR HOUSE OF COMMONS AIDE I wrote and researched policy documents on local and national issues; wrote speeches for campaigns, debates, and business events. I also personally programmed a databasing application (MS Access) to manage office comms.

Education

Makers Academy (May 2016 - Aug 2016)

Makers Academy afforded me the opportunity to learn professional best practices, surrounded by some truly great programmers. I developed my curiosity and hungry passion for code, with focus on becoming an independent learner and problem-solver. They offer a firm grounding in the principles of software craftsmanship: OOP, TDD, SOLID, BDD.

Physics 2:1 (BSc & ARCS): Imperial College London (Oct 2005 to July 2008)

I focussed on astrophysics, plasma physics, and the practicalities of nuclear fusion energy as a future energy source. Wrote a thesis on the physical and political implications of the atom bomb on the 20th century.

Final Year Degree Project (C++)

I received 93% for an investigation into the process of evolution using a computer simulation. Wrote the program from scratch, modelling biological systems. Praised particularly for the ability to analyse great amounts of data, to spot patterns and anomalies, present them accessibly and to quantify the results in a manner that the assessor, who worked in this field, had never seen before.

Interests

CACIN - The Political Creative Industries Network (2008 - 2017) | DIRECTOR

I developed and maintained relationships with many key players in the tech & creative sectors, and ran regular panels and drinks receptions across the UK, centering on issues from the digital single market to diversity in the media.

The Digital Bazaar, Tate South Lambeth Library (2009 - 2013) | FOUNDING VOLUNTEER & IT EXPERT Taught basic computer, smartphone and other technology use to struggling members of the Lambeth community (many of whom did not have English as a first language). Runners-up for the CILIP Libraries Change Lives Award 2012.

Other:

Tech Tinkering – I'm a Linux user at home (Fedora, Debian, Ubuntu, Mint). I have a home-made NAS made with a Raspberry Pi, and a homemade server – also running on Raspbian. I code small apps (usually in ES6 now) and run them from that server.

Music - I have an extensively musical education. I received the music scholarship to my secondary school. I sang in a Christ Church Cathedral Choir Oxford, and played the Saxophone, Violin, Piano, and guitar.

Tennis - I play regularly with a variety of partners and am coached professionally.

Cooking - I love cooking and spend a great deal of time in the kitchen. My recipes are popular on Instagram.